Hello and welcome back to another
video with ItsDrDan, and today we're
going to be specifically looking
at alkanes and how to name them
whenever they have different isomers
of propyl and butyls as substituents.
So one of the big things about these
different groups is that with propyl
and butyl is that they start adding
a lot more carbons, meaning that
eventually they're not always going to
be just in a straight chain anymore.
We're going to start seeing
some different shapes arise.
So the first one is, let's kind of
just focus on just propyl, right?
Propyl if you remember is three carbons,
so therefore if you have like let's say
a chain like this one here, so if I were
to let's say add a propyl onto it, well
the big thing is whenever you start kind
of adding these bigger chains is that
there's kind of a limit to where you
can realistically place them, um, just
because if you sort of place them like
too close to the ends, it's going to end
up redefining your longest parent chain.
So typically you only ever have them
in the middle and they tend to be
even a little bit more rarer and
especially in terms of organic chemistry
one and introductory chemistry.
So if I kind of have this in the middle
here, um, and I wanted to name it.
So if I kind of named it from
the left and I say one, two,
three, four, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.
Well, how would I end up naming this?
Well, if you remember from my previous
lessons or from my other videos, that
this would be 5 methyl, or sorry, not 5
methyl, 5 propyl nonane would be the name.
Now, is this the only shape?
Well, there's other shapes possible,
and it has to do with isomers.
So if you remember, isomers are whenever
you have the same exact chemical formula.
Um, but it has a different structure.
So propyl has one of them.
So essentially for propyl, it can
actually form this Y shape that is right
next to me where it's isosymmetric.
So you can see that when you look
at this, uh, structure here that the
R, remember that's the rest of the
molecule, so that's referring to your
chain, It's connected to a single carbon
and then it's split on both sides.
And you can see that too in the skeletal
structure as well that it has that split.
So essentially if you ever were to put
this in a structure it allows it to get a
little bit closer to the ends as a result.
So let's say if I had my nonane and I
ended up putting it let's say on carbon
number three, and I have that split.
Well, how exactly would
you go through naming it?
You do the exact same
process as before, right?
We would say that, hey, we have nonane,
which is that nine member, uh, chain.
And we would end up putting
where that isopropyl is, which
is at the third position.
And you would say three isopropyl.
Nonane, and that's because
of the shape of it, right?
So that's something else.
One more thing to really look for is
that whenever you have this special
shape of this Y shape here That
means that oh you have an isopropyl.
Now, is that the only one?
Well, I've kind of saw at the beginning
it was propyls and butyls both
have them And also Pentels as well.
But we're not going to do
that in this particular video.
Let's take a look at Beutels specifically.
Now when it comes to Beutels, same idea.
They really need to be in the middle
of the chain because you got to keep in
mind that if you want a Beutel group,
It, it's four carbons long, so it's
really easy for it to redefine a chain.
So I'm going to put it right here
in the middle, just to kind of
go through naming this structure.
So butyl is four carbons long.
So if I go through this, we can see
that, all right, I'll name number across.
So once again, this is also a nonane.
So we have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9.
So nonane, and we can see that our
butyl is at number five in this one.
So what we would say is five butyl.
nonane for the name.
Now what kind of shapes do you have?
Well there's other than nonane, other
than butyl, so being that this is a
straight chain butyl, and the same
goes for propyl, is that it's very
common to see the letter n to say
that this is the normal form of butyl.
So whenever you see a little n,
and let's say if you look something
up, there's a reason for that,
that means that it is normal.
Now, typically we do not include that,
and it's very uncommon to do that, and
in fact in my classes I don't ask anybody
to do that because it's not normal to
do it, even though it's called normal.
So when it comes to the different
shapes of isomers, well, they have
these little unique shapes to them.
So the first one, if you kind of look
on the far left here is also ISO.
So you can see that we
have the same idea here.
This one kind of reminds me a little bit
of like, almost like a little mermaid
tail is kind of the way to think about it.
So you have the tail at the end and then
essentially like swimming or maybe like
a dolphin tail is one way to look at it.
Now, what makes this one, um, different
than essentially the one that we
had earlier is the fact that there
is an extra carbon, uh, right here.
So you can see that we have, uh, going
through these, we have one, two, three,
four carbons, which if you remember, butyl
is four carbons, and then they have the
condensed structure here to show as well.
There's also sec butyl.
So sec, it's coming from secondary, so
it's sort of like the classification,
but it's So, with this one, right, you
can see this carbon here in the middle,
uh, that's connecting the two sides.
You can see it's uneven as a result.
So it has one, two carbons on each side.
That's where the secondary comes from.
And then you have your
fourth carbon as well.
So be secondary.
And the last one I always are
kind of referred to as a little
bit looks like reminds me of like
a chicken foot or a bird foot.
Um, and then with this one, you can
kind of see the three, the three
little toes that are pointing up.
So you have a one, two, three, and
then the fourth one in the middle.
And that one is tert butyl, so it
has CH3s all around the carbon.
So that's what we're going to be
seeing right here with that carbon.
Um, and then each one of them
has its own unique shape to it.
So let's kind of practice trying
to identify some of these and to
go through a couple examples of it.
So that way we, we are familiar
with it when it comes to your class.
All right, let's take a look.
So for the following problem, we're
going to write the IUPAC name for
each of the following molecules.
So let's go through our steps.
The first thing we're going to do is
we're going to identify what our longest,
uh, carbon chain is or our parent chain.
So with this one, you might be able to
quickly see it that if I highlight across,
We can see that we have a very long chain.
So if we end up numbering that,
mean that you want to start the
numbering, uh, closest to your
substituent or your branch.
So we have 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6,
7, and your branch is this
specific kind of shape over here.
So if I highlight it, right, we can
see that we have this unique shape.
Now when it comes to identifying it, the
first thing you got to do is you want to.
Determine how many carbons do
you have, and you can see that
we have, uh, four carbons.
In this structure, so we got 1234.
So that's going to be one
of your beautiful shapes.
So when we're trying to look at
this, well, I excluded all the shapes
here and you want to try to play
a little bit of a matching game.
But ideally, you want to be able to
memorize these because he won't have
maybe these as accessible on, let's say,
an exam or maybe in a lab right away.
So it's good to know what they are.
So you'll see that if I look at all the
butyl shapes, the one that kind of sticks
out the most is actually that sec butyl.
So the one that's in the middle, and
that's going to be our shape for this one.
So let's write down our name.
So the first thing was, right,
you just write down the parent
chain, and it was seven.
So that's going to be
heptane is for seven.
And then we have essentially our branch,
which is located at carbon number three.
So what we're going to simply do is take
three and then we'll say three sec butyl.
And that would be the name for the sec
butyl heptane would be the entire name.
Let's try another.
So if I'm going to look at this
one, well, Oh, we got something
a little interesting here.
We have a ring structure.
and one of the groups.
Well, you might be able to quickly see
that, well, this guy actually quickly
matches the one that's right next to,
which is three carbons, right, is what's
in this, uh, particular car, this branch.
So it's going to be this isopropyl.
It's the only unique one for isopropyl.
So what we're going to do is we're going
to start by writing down isopropyl.
And being that's a ring structure
and it's the only Only branch,
you do not have to number it.
The only time you do have to
go through numbering is if
you have multiple branches.
In that case, you want to go via priority.
So whatever's the most important
thing, typically functional
groups, which is something that'll
be covered in future videos.
So isopropyl, and being that this
is a ring structure, we have to
count how many carbons we have.
We have one, two, three,
four, five, and six.
So we use the prefix cyclo.
For a ring and being that it is
six, it's going to be cyclohexane.
So it's isopropyl cyclohexane
would be the complete name.
Let's do another.
So right here, I also have
another one as well, right?
And the same rules kind of apply.
You want to find what your
longest carbon chain is.
So you quickly can see that,
oh, if I go across, I have five.
Right, and that one's going to be
your longest chain in this case.
Now there are other options here
that you could have had, right?
You could go across, that's the easy one.
Or if you kind of noticed, you could have
actually like wrapped around and done this
as well as five, and the name is actually
going to be different in this situation.
Now the thing is, with these specific
shapes, it actually helps simplify names.
Right, if I pick the one that's like
the dark blue color, I would have
had three different methyl groups
and it would have been a little
bit more complicated, possibly.
Maybe not.
It kind of depends on
what your preference is.
But using something that's like a tert
butyl, which is this specific one here,
it actually allows you to really be
able to sort of consolidate things and
it can make things a little bit easier.
It's not always, it's personal
preference, but there's not, in this
case there wouldn't be one right or
wrong answer, but you typically do
see a lot of more favoritism in IUPAC.
Towards those special structure
names when it's possible.
So we have five.
So that would be pentane, right?
So that is what we would use.
Now we want to alphabetize
our different groups.
So would I go by the T
for tert butyl or not?
That's really the question.
Well, being that you want to go by
what the actual branch is, so butyl,
you go by B, not by the T part of it.
So you always go off of
what the actual branch is.
So B becomes before M, which is the
methyl that is attached here as well.
So just to kind of highlight
where the methyl is.
So what we would end up writing is we
would have three T butyl, and then you
have your methyl, Which we have it had in
green there, and then we'd put to methyl.
And the only reason we have methyl
coming first is because of alphabetical
order, or sorry, methyl coming
second, uh, butyl comes before.
Okay?
Now that's the whole idea of trying
to name these special structures.
This was a little bit of a different
one, just kind of helping with
more additional practice with this.
If you still need help on just branching
and you haven't seen my video on how
to name with branches, and I'm going
to have more videos coming out on
organic chemistry, so please feel free
to hit that like and subscribe button
if it's your first time here and you
need help with your class um, in this.
Alright, thank you so much for listening,
and I hope that this video helped, and if
you need additional help, say something
in the comments, I can be able to try
to lead you in the right direction.
Alright, I'll see you later.
Bye now!